Guide to the Marius de Zayas Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Marius de Zayas Papers,
1914-1948
Zayas, Marius de.
5.5 linear ft (3,000 items in 13 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078697
Biographical Note
Painter. Marius de Zayas (1880-1961?) was a portrait painter and director of the Modern Gallery in New York. His father, Rafael de Zayas Enriquez (1848-1932) was a prominent Mexican man-of-letters and politician who was known as "The Grand Old Man of Mexico"
Scope and Content
A large collection of the letters and manuscripts of Rafael de Zayas Enriquez, as well as a miscellaneous collection of letters and bills of sale pertaining to the activities of Marius de Zayas. The Rafael de Zayas Enriquez papers include letters, manuscripts, books, and clippings. His writings reflect his many and varied talents and interests: history, poetry, sociology, novels, and plays. His manuscripts and books comprise the bulk of this collection. The photocopies of letters to Marius de Zayas pertain to the magazine "291" and the Modern Gallery. There is correspondence from Pablo Picasso, Diego Rivera, Paul Guillaume, Max Jacob, Agnes Meyer, Alfred Stieglitz, Tristan Tzara, and Max Weber. The majority of these letters are unpublished although some of the most important ones appear in Michel Sanouillet's Francis Picabia et "291" (Paris, 1966).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Photocopies of Letters to Marius de Zayas
Series II: Letters tand by Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
Series III: Manuscripts
Series IV: Documents Relating to Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
Series V: Printed Material Relating to Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
Series VI: Clippings by Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
Subjects
Modern Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Enriquez, Rafael de Zayas.; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946.; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973.; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957.; Guillaume, Paul.; Jacob, Max.; Meyer, Agnes.; Tzara, Tristan, 1896-1963.; Weber, Max.; Sanouillet, Michel.; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York.; Art--Periodicals.; Painters.; Portrait-painters.; [Three-nine-one] "391."--magazine.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Access Restrictions
Collection is shelved off-site and requires advance notice of intent to use.
Acquisition
1972 M-72 Zayas, Rodrigues de Gift
Gift of Rodrigo de Zayas, 1972.
Gift of Nicole de Zayas, 1997.
- Series I: Photocopies of Letters to Marius de Zayas
  - Guillaume, Paul To Marius de Zayas, France, [n.d.] & 29 May 1917, (1 a.l.s., 1 postcard, 1 t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jacob, Max To Marius de Zayas, [n.p.], [1915 & 1916], (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Meyer, Agnes To Marius de Zayas, N.Y., [1915] & 1916, (2 a.l.s., 1 t.l., 1 t.l.s. (from Eugene Meyer)) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Picabia, Francis To Marius de Zayas, [n.p.], 1916, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picasso, Pablo To Marius de Zayas, Paris, 14 September 1916, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rivera, Diego To Marius de Zayas, Paris, 1915 & 1916, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stieglitz, Alfred To Marius de Zayas, N.Y., 1915, (5 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tzara, Trista & Marcel Janco To Marius de Zayas, Zurich, 28 December 1916, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Weber, Max To Marius de Zayas, N.Y., 18 November 1948, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Zayas, Marius de To Alfred Stieglitz, N.Y., 1915, (1 a.l.s. (photocopy), 1 t.l. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [With a.l.s. (photocopy) to Jorge, 7 September 1915]
  - Zayas, Marius de Photocopies of letters, accounts, inventories, etc. re. his art business, N.Y., [n.d.] & 1914 - 1948, () (Box 1, Folder 11 - 18)
- Series II: Letters tand by Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de To Marius de Zayas, Mexico, 24 August 1913, (1 a.l., 22 pages) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Letters from various people, [v.p.], [n.d.] & 1872-1932, () (Box 1, Folder 20 - 68)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  Mostly by Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
  - Cestero, Ferdinand Poem relating to Rafel de Zayas Enriquez, Puerto Rico, 10 September 1905, (1 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Collselo, G. del Soneto, Mexico, 1893, (1 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Zayas, [Nicole?] de Notes on the collection, [N.Y.], [n.d.], (1 page a.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de "Anakreonte Teyo". Estudo de la vida y de las obras del famoso poeta, [n.p.], [n.d.], (151 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Archipielago del Norte, [n.p.], [n.d.], (16 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Aventuras de Junior y Pedrito, N.Y., 16 November 1963, (ca 500 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Adventuring Across the Rio Grande, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca 500 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 75 & 76)
    [In Spanish]
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Adventuring Across the Rio Grande, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca 500 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 77 & 78)
    [In English]
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Aristodemo [Play], [n.p.], [n.d.], (20 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cinematograficas: coleccion de articulos publicados en el "Cine Mundial", [n.p.], [n.d.], (238 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Conde de Villamediana [Play], [n.p.], [n.d.], (110 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Conde de Villamediana [Play], [n.p.], [n.d.], (110 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 83)
    [With related material]
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Crimen, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca 120 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cuentos de Carnaval: Recuerdos de Venecia, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca 40 page t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cuentos, [n.p.], [n.d.], (367 page t.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cuentos del Cuartel, [n.p.], [n.d.], (50 page a.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cuentos del Cuartel, Mexico, 22 December 1906, (50 page a.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cuentos del Cuartel, [n.p.], [n.d.], (150 page t.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Cuentos del Cuartel, [n.p.], [n.d.], (150 page t.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Discursos, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca. 60 page t.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Disquisicion del Orign de la Raza Maya, [n.p.], 1930, (13 page t.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Disquisiciones Literaris: Coleccion de articulos sobre estetica, y juicios criticos, Mexoco, 1906, (ca 50 page t.ms.) (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Entre los dos Abismos, [n.p.], [n.d.], (8 page t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Escombros [Poems], [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca 70 page t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Evolucion en Criminologia: Estudio Juridico-Sociologico, [n.p.], [n.d.], (300 page t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 97 & 98)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Evolucion en Criminologia: Estudio Juridico-Sociologico, [n.p.], [n.d.], (300 page t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 99 & 100)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Evolucion Feminista, N.Y., 8 August 1924, (154 page t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Hamlet Principe Dedinamarca, [n.p.], [n.d.], (74 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Historia, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca. 600 page t.ms. & a.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 103 - 105)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Hombre Cris: Primera Parte de la Trilogia, [n.p.], [n.d.], (92 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Luciernagas [Poems], N.Y., [n.d.], (170 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Manuscripts (incomplete, fragments, etc.), N.Y., [n.d.], (ca. 50 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Matter, Energy, Spirit, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de The Maya Vestal [Novel], [n.p.], [n.d.], (230 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Mi Homenaje a Cervantes, [n.p.], [n.d.], (100 page t.ms.) (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Mi Libro de Oro, [n.p.], [n.d.], (170 page t.ms.) (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Mi Libro de Oro, [n.p.], [n.d.], (170 page t.ms.) (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Mi Libro de Oro, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 a.ms. notebooks) (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Microbinas [Poems], [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 a.ms. notebooks) (Box 7, Folder 115 & 116)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Microbinas [Poems], [n.p.], [n.d.], (149 page a.ms. notebook) (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Miscelleneous fragments, [n.p.], [n.d.], (10 page a.ms.) (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de [Mythology], [n.p.], [n.d.], (107 page t.ms. (incomplete)) (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Naufragio de un Alma [Play], [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca 150 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Naufragio de un Alma [Play], [n.p.], [n.d.], (86 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de [Natural Sciences/Philosophy], [n.p.], [n.d.], (242 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Paginas Sueltas, [n.p.], ca. 1928, (150 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Panhispanismo y Panamericanismo, N.Y., July 1919, (107 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Picaros y Hombres de Bien, [n.p.], [n.d.], (105 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de [Play, untitled], [n.p.], [n.d.], (25 page a.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de [Poems], [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca. 50 page t.ms.) (Box 8, Folder 128 & 129)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Prediccion de la Bruja [Novel], Mexico, 2 November 1907, (ca. 250 page t.ms. & a.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 130 & 131)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Prizes Awarded to Rafael de Zayas Enriquez, [n.p.], [n.d.], (7 page t.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Prizes Awarded to Rafael de Zayas Enriquez, [n.p.], [n.d.], (7 page t.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Prologo, [n.p.], [n.d.], (5 page a.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Sonnets, N.Y., July 1929, (49 page t.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Satan Blanco, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca. 200 page t.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 135)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Satan Blanco, [n.p.], [n.d.], (57 page t.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 136)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Suicidio, [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca. 200 page a.ms.) (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Los Tartufos [Play], [n.p.], [n.d.], (129 page t.ms., 1 volume) (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Las Teorias de Mi Amego Don Primitivo Practico, [n.p.], [n.d.], (73 page t.ms., 1 volume) (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Xtabentun La Vestal Maya, N.Y., 23 October 1921, (ca. 225 page t.ms.) (Box 10, Folder 140)
- Series IV: Documents Relating to Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Accounts, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page a.ms.) (Box 10, Folder 141)
  - Medical diploma of C. Jose Martines Ancira, Mexico, 22 May 1877, (1 page p.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 142)
  - College of Estado Certificate, Mexico, 16 September 1902, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 143)
  - Consul of Mexico. San Francisco Documents (4), San Francisco, 1903-1906, (4 page t.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 144)
  - Prefecture de Police. France Extrait du Registre D'Immatriculation, Paris, 1915, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 145)
  - Juarez, Benito Document re. elections, Mexico, 16 December 1899, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Consul of Mexico. London Document re. De Zayas Enriquez, London, 1914, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Consul of Mexico. Paris Certificate re. De Zayas Enriquez, Paris, 1926, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Treasury. Mexico Document re. De Zayas Enriquez, Mexico, 1904, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Military Association. Mexico Document re. De Zayas Enriquez, Mexico, 1879, (1 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 150)
  - Secretaria de Guerra y Marina. Mexico Plana Mayor del Ejercito, Mexico, 1899, (11 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - Library of Congress Copyright notice, Washington, 3 October 1912, (1 card t.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - Photocopies of documents, Mexico & Peru, [n.d.] & 1903, (2 page a.d.s.) (Box 10, Folder 153)
- Series V: Printed Material Relating to Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Avicultura Practica, Mexico: Ofic. Tip. de la Secretaria de Fomento, 1897, (1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Biographical material, [n.p.], 1910, (3 clippings) (Box 10, Folder 155)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de "Consideraciones Sobre la Raza Blanca. Su Origen", America magazine, [n.d.], (12 pages) (Box 10, Folder 156)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de "Cuentos del Cuartel - Un Valiente", America magazine & Revista Latino-Americana, [n.d.], (14 pages) (Box 10, Folder 157)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Elementos de Moral, Veracruz: Tipografia "Comercial" de R. de Zayas, 1875, (60 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 158)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Elevacion y Caida del Gral. Porfirio Diaz, Merida Yucatan: Imp. de "La Revista de Merida", 1911, (206 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 159)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Exposito, Veracruz: Tip. de R. de Zayas, 1882, (46 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 160)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Fisiologia del Crimen, Veracruz: Imprenta de R. de Zayas, 1885, (267 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Historia de la Reforma en Mexico, Merida Yucatan, 1926, (172 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Historia de la Reforma en Mexico, Merida Yucatan, 1926, (172 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 163)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Historia de la Reforma en Mexico, Merida Yucatan, 1926, (172 pages, 1 volume) (Box 10, Folder 164)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Los Ilotas, Veracruz: Tip. de R. de Zayas, 1887, (100 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de "The Mexican Crisis", The Financial Review of Reviews, 1914, (10 pages) (Box 11, Folder 166)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de "Mi Bandera", Revista Latino-Americana, [n.d.], (3 pages) (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Oceanida, Veracruz: Tip de R. de Zayas, 1887, (236 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Oceanida, Veracruz: Tip de R. de Zayas, 1887, (236 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 169)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Poemas Sudras, Mexico: Tip. Artistica, 1903, (64 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 170)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Poemas Sudras, Mexico: Tip. Artistica, 1903, (64 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 170)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Reforma el Segundo Imperio, Lagos de Moreno, 1904, (206 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 171)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Remordimiento, [n.p.], [n.d.], (123 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 172)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Secreto de Carlos, [n.p.], [n.d.], (147 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de El Teniente de los Gavilanes, N.Y.: D. Appleton and Co., 1902, (341 pages, 1 volume) (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de [La Verdad de] 25 de Junio, [n.p.], [n.d.], (159 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12, Folder 175)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Verdad Sobre el 25 de Junio, Merida Yucatan, 1919, (113 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12, Folder 176)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de La Verdad Sobre el 25 de Junio, Merida Yucatan, 1919, (113 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12, Folder 177)
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Violetas: Periodico Literario, Veracruz, 1869, (276 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12, Folder 178)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 179 & 180)
  - Redarez Saint Reme Odes, Paris: Librairie de L. Hachette, 1854, (240 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12, Folder 181)
  - Ignacio Gutierrez Zamora Contando un Viaje, [n.p.], 1934, (89 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12, Folder 182)
  - Artemio de Valle-Arizpe Historia, tradiciones y leyendas de calles de Mexico, Mexico, 1957, (834 pages, 1 volume) (Box 12)
- Series VI: Clippings by Rafael de Zayas Enriquez
  - Zayas Enriquez, Rafael de Clippings of articles, Mexico & N.Y., [v.d.], (ca. 500 clippings) (Box 13)